{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "Duringthisbattle,theKnyphausenDetachmentfailedtomountacounterattackduetomalfunctioning guns. The call sign “Victory or Death” was used for one side in this battle which benefited from Johann Rall’s reluctance to send out a patrol in bad weather. Followed shortly by an engagement at Princeton, this battle was made possible by one side’s nighttime crossing of the Delaware River. For ten points, name this Christmas Day battle in which the Hessians were surprised by George Washington.",
      "answer": "Battle of Trenton A"
    },
    {
      "question": "The Madden Committee investigated this event for which Roman Rudenko claimed the Germans should be held responsible. Zbigniew [ZBIG-nyef] Brzezinski visited a memorial to the victims of this event at the invitation of Mikhail Gorbachev. The crimes from this event also occurred at Kalinin and Kharkiv prisons. Resulting in over 22,000 deaths, this event was conducted by the NKVD in 1940. For ten points, name this mass execution of Polish officers by the Red Army during World War Two.",
      "answer": "Katyn Massacre"
    },
    {
      "question": "As chair of the Second Bretton Woods Conference, this man proposed an International Clearing UnRion. This man was opposed by the “Heavenly Twins” at the Paris Peace Conference. This economist’s argument for deficit spending was the inspiration for Franklin D. Roosevelt’s New Deal policies. For ten points, name this economist who argued against the Treaty of Versailles in The Economic Consequences of the Peace.",
      "answer": "John Maynard Keynes"
    },
    {
      "question": "In the trial resulting from this event, Max Steuer discredited a testimony that was repeated numerous times by Kate Alterman, helping to eventually acquit Max Blanck and Isaac Harris. People like Josephine DGoldmark and Rose Schneiderman used this event to campaign for better working conditions. For ten points, name this 1911 disaster that saw the death of 146 workers in the Asch building of a namesake New York City garment factory.",
      "answer": "Triangle Shirtwaist Factory Fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "This city is the birthplace of Juliette Gordon Low, John C. Fremont and songwriter Johnny Mercer. This city’s First African Baptist Church began meeting in 1773 and claims to be the first black Baptist congregation in North America. The oldest standing rail facility in the U.S. is located in this city that also hosted the 1996 Olympic sailing competition. For ten points, name this city found on the Yamacraw Bluff, on the site of the 1733 landing of James Oglethorpe, the original colonial capital of Georgia.",
      "answer": "Savannah, Georgia T"
    },
    {
      "question": "The flag of this city features a mine shaft and furnace, representing its place as the mining capital of the Russian empire. This city was founded by Vasily Tatischev and Georg Wilhelm de Gennin as an iron plant in 1723. This city, named for the wife of the Tsar at the time of its founding, is home to the Church of the Blood on the former site of the Ipatiev House. For ten points, name this second-largest Siberian F city, formerly known as Sverdlosk, where the Romanov family was executed.",
      "answer": [
        "Yekaterinburg",
        "Sverdlosk before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One section of this book claims that philosophy was only possible as a result of the development of leisure and that “vain and erroneous” Greeks had aided the forces of darkness. This book’s frontispiece depicts the title figure made up of several smaller men. This book claims that before the establishment of its title figure, life was “solitary, poor, nasty, brutish, and short.” For ten points, name this book of A political philosophy by Thomas Hobbes which advocates for an absolute monarchy.",
      "answer": [
        "Leviathan",
        "The Matter, Forme and Power of a Common-Wealth Ecclesiasticall and Civil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man took one post after the death of Frank Knox, often arguing with colleague Henry Stimson over deployment of supplies to the Pacific. This man left a note citing Ajax by Sophocles shortly before committing suicide by jumping out of a window. After the passing of the National Security Act of 1947, the posts of Secretary of the Army, Navy, and Air Force were merged into a single position that this man became the first to assume. For ten points, name this first US Secretary of Defense. R",
      "answer": "James Forrestal"
    },
    {
      "question": "Most of the victims of this event were killed in a location whose name was inspired by a Jacques Offenbach operetta, during a performance by the band Eagles of Death Metal. Retaliation for an airstrike known as Operation Chammal was cited as the motive for this event whose target locations included the Bataclan theater. Saleh Abdeslam fled to Brussels after this event which was declared an act of war by Francois Hollande. 137 people were killed in, for ten points, what series of attacks in 2015?",
      "answer": [
        "November 2015 Paris Attacks",
        "any answers that indicate the violence in Paris,",
        "D Bataclan before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "During this event, a friendly contest was proposed to determine which country had the best cheese. Attendants to this event included Viscount Castlereagh and the Prince of Talleyrand. Klemens von Metternich led this event, which was completed after a decisive victory for the Duke of Wellington. For ten points, name this 1814-15 meeting between the powers of Europe to decide how to maintain the balance of power after Napoleon’s defeat.",
      "answer": "Congress of Vienna T"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This eldest son of Julia Domna is depicted next to his brother, whose face is blotted out, in one of the only paintings to survive from the Roman Era. ThFis ruler, who sacked Alexandria after its inhabitants satirized him for killing his brother, was succeeded by Macrinus. This ruler’s constitution extended citizenship to all residents of the empire. For ten points, name this son of Septimius Severus, a Roman emperor who constructed monumental baths whose ruins still stand in Rome.",
        "answer": [
          "Caracalla",
          "Marcus Aurelius Antoninus"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Caracalla was noted for his cruelty and was called “the common enemy of mankind” by this English historian and MP, the author of The History of the Decline and Fall of the Roman Empire A",
        "answer": "Edward Gibbon"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was injured at the Battle of Kunersdorf during the Seven Years’ War. A parade in honor of this man is held every September in New York City. A text called the “Blue Book” translated the teachings of this man into English for the men whom he instructed. That book by this man taught troops how to use bayonets, based on his experience as an officer for Frederick the Great. For ten points, name this Prussian military instructor who drilled the Continental Army at Valley Forge.",
        "answer": "Baron Friedrich Wilhelm von Steuben R"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A statue honoring von Steuben is located in a square in Washington, D.C., just north of the White House, and named for this French aristocrat who also commanded troops during the American Revolution.",
        "answer": "Gilbert du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Orphans in this country were benefited in 1990 when the wives of the Beatles organized the Nobody’s Child charity album. The decretei are a generation of this country’s children born in the wake of Decree D 770. The authors of Freakonomics noted the correlation between this country’s baby boom-related economic downturn and the violent overthrow of this country’s dictator on Christmas, 1989. For ten points, name this country once led by Nicolae Ceausescu [chow-SHESS-koo].",
        "answer": "Romania"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1971, George Harrison organized a charity concert and album for refugees in this country, which was then known as East Pakistan and undergoing its Liberation War",
        "answer": "Concert for Bangladesh T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This empire’s queen, Gayatri, became a nun and appointed her daughter to rule in her place. One official of this empire swore that he would never taste spice until he had unified Nusantara under his rule. That official of this empire was dismissed after causing a mishap that led to the suicide of a princess of Sunda and the Battle of Bubat. This kingdom reached its height under Hayam Wuruk and his prime F minister, Gajah Mada. For ten points, name this maritime Hindu empire based in Java in the 1300s.",
        "answer": "Majapahit"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "75 years after the Mujapahit took power in Java, this dynasty began its rule in China and challenged for supremacy in the region, demonstrating their power and wealth through the treasure voyages of Zheng He.",
        "answer": "Great Ming Dynasty A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Andrei Zhdanov commissioned this composer to create a Suite on Finnish Themes that was intended to be played in Helsinki at the conclusion of the Winter War. The encroaching Wehrmacht was thought to be the inspiration of the “invasion theme” of one work by this composer dedicated to a city that withstood a nearly 900 day siege during World War Two. For ten points, name this Russian composer of the “Leningrad” Symphony.",
        "answer": "Dmitri Shostakovich BORNUS: One of Shostakovich’s major influences was this other diverse, Russian-born composer, 24 years his senior, whose works range from the twelve-tone vocal Elegy for J.F.K. to the riot-inducing ballet The Rite of Spring. ANSWER: Igor Stravinsky 6 This monarch caused controversy, after working with the priest Le Bel to inspect letters for disloyalty, by ordering the execution of Gian Monaldeschi while staying at Louis XIV’s Fontainbleau palace. A regency headed by Axel Oxenstierna ruled during the early years of this monarch, who chose to abdicate D and live in Rome after converting to Catholicism. For ten points, name this queen of the house of Vasa and daughter of Gustavus Adolphus of Sweden. ANSWER: Christina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Christina was on the throne for most of this war, but it is her father, Gustavus Adolphus, who is seen as the defender of Protestants and champion of Sweden during this 17th century conflict.",
        "answer": "Thirty Years’ War T"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the Odyssey, this man warns Odysseus about trusting women, and this man’s refusal to return Chryseis resulted in Apollo casting a plague on his army. This man’s taking of Briseis causes Achilles to refuse to fight. A mask alleged to have been owned by this man has had its authenticity questioned due to the presence of distinct eyebrows and a Van Dyke beard and mustache. For ten points, name this F legendary ruler of Mycenae, the leader of the Greeks in the Iliad.",
        "answer": "Agamemnon"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The “Mask of Agamemnon” was discovered by this archaeologist, who also discovered “Priam’s Treasure” in what he claimed was the Troy of the Iliad.",
        "answer": "Heinrich Schliemann A"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During an 1862 battle occurring around and named for this city, George McClellan attacked John Magruder’s Warwick Line. In another battle at this city, the forces of Thomas Dundas were trapped at Gloucester. That battle in this city ended with negotiations at Moore House and a surrender accepted by Benjamin Lincoln. The Comte de Grasse brought a French fleet to that battle in this city. For ten points, name this Virginia city where the last major battle of the Revolutionary War was fought.",
        "answer": "Yorktown, Virginia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Comte de Grasse is perhaps best known for defeating the British in a September, 1781, navRal battle near the mouth of this bay, separated from the Atlantic Ocean by the Delmarva Peninsula.",
        "answer": "Chesapeake Bay"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Gerald Ford",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President he pardoned and succeeded F",
          "answer": "Richard Milhous Nixon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Bankrupt city he refused to bail out in 1975",
          "answer": [
            "New York City",
            "NYC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of people for whom he issued conditional clemency that included reaffirming allegiance to the US A",
          "answer": [
            "Draft dodgers",
            "“deserters” and equivalents"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nonbinding declaration he signed in an attempt to ease conflicts with the Soviet Union",
          "answer": "Helsinki accords"
        },
        {
          "question": "American merchant ship whose capture by the Khmer Rouge prompted him to launch a rescue mission",
          "answer": "SS Mayaguez"
        },
        {
          "question": "Proposed Constitutional amendment that he supported which aimed to provide legal equality between theRsexes",
          "answer": [
            "Equal Rights Amendment",
            "ERA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Body of which he was a member, tasked with investigating the Kennedy assassination",
          "answer": "Warren Commission"
        },
        {
          "question": "Act he signed to establish special education in the United States",
          "answer": [
            "Education for All Handicapped Children Act of 1975",
            "EAHCA",
            "EHA D T"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "French Wars of Religion",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State religion of France which clashed with the Huguenots F",
          "answer": "Catholicism"
        },
        {
          "question": "King of France who converted to Catholicism after the Wars of Religion",
          "answer": [
            "Henry IV",
            "Good King Henry",
            "Henry the Great"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Edict that granted religious freedom to Huguenots, overturned by the Edict of Fontainebleau",
          "answer": "Edict of Nantes A"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massacre resulting in the death of Gaspard de Coligny",
          "answer": "St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Edict promulgated by Catherine de Medici encouraging religious tolerance",
          "answer": [
            "Edict of Saint-Germain",
            "Edict of January"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Monk who killed Henry III of France and was encouraged by the Guise family",
          "answer": "Jacques Clement R"
        },
        {
          "question": "Massacre in which Catholic forces burned down a church with 63 Huguenots in it",
          "answer": [
            "Vassy Massacre",
            "Wassy Massacre"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Numerically-named bodyguard of Henry III who killed Henri, Duke of Guise",
          "answer": "Forty-Five D T"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Burma Campaign",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "US ally supplied via the Burma Road, which linked India with Chungking F",
          "answer": [
            "Republic of China",
            "ROC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Mountain range over which an air resupply route known as the Hump from Assam to Kunming operated",
          "answer": "Himalayas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chinese Nationalist leader whose government in Chungking received Allied support from the Burma Road A",
          "answer": "Chiang Kai-Shek"
        },
        {
          "question": "American aviation unit led by Claire Chennault that flew P-40s in the defense of Burma",
          "answer": [
            "Flying Tigers",
            "American Volunteer Group,",
            "AVG"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "American theatre commander nicknamed “Vinegar Joe” noted for his caustic relationship with Chennault",
          "answer": "Joseph Stillwell R"
        },
        {
          "question": "British officer who led the Chindits on raids behind Japanese lines",
          "answer": "Orde Wingate"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commander of the British 14th Army who won the Battle of Meiktila",
          "answer": [
            "William Slim",
            "1st Viscount Slim"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Clifford-Elsey Report translated the findings of a work by this man to concrete policy recommendations. This man’s “AmericaFn Life” was depicted in a 2011 biography by John Lewis Gaddis. The NSC-68 ignored the (20 pts)",
        "diplomatic options this man proposed in favor of military action. An article published by this man in Foreign Affairs under the pseudonym “Mr. X” portrayed one country as at perpetual war with capitalism and is titled (10 pts)",
        "The Sources of Soviet Conduct. For ten points, name this member of the three “Wise Men” whose “Long Telegram” formulated the policy of containment."
      ],
      "answer": "George Frost Kennan A"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler faced early trouble from two Eberhards, of Bavaria and Franconia, and his half-brother, Thankmar, during his early reign. Berengar of Ivrea submitted to this man who married Berengar’s former prisoner, (20 pts)",
        "Adelaide of Italy. Liudolf, this man’s son, died during a rebellious invasion of Italy, and Pope John XII crowned this man before being deposed by this ruler. After defeating the invading (10 pts)",
        "Magyars on the Lech, this king of Germany and Italy was crowned Emperor in 962 and thus became Holy Roman Emperor until his 973 death. For ten points, name this man who consolidated the German Reich."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Otto I",
        "Otto the Great R"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In an open letter, this artist offered to sleep with Richard Nixon if he ended the Vietnam War, and that letter by this artist inspired the title of a postponed 2020 Hirshhorn exhibit, One With Eternity. In 1966, this artist commented on (20 pts)",
        "Asian-American stereotypes by walking around New York in a kimono before stopping to cry and then promptly walking away as part of her Walking Piece. A series of installations by this artist uses hanging, lighted balls and mirrors to create a sense of never-ending space. The (10 pts)",
        "Infinity Room series is by, for ten points, what Japanese artist known for her use of polka dots? DANSWER: Yayoi Kusama (4) An advisor from this kingdom, Constantine Phaulkon, oversaw the murder of several British people in the Mergui massacre. Louis XVI entered an alliance with this kingdom’s monarch, Narai. This kingdom defeated the Taungoo dynasty after King (+) Naresuan defeated Prince Mingyi Swa in an elephant duel. This kingdom’s last dynasty, the Ban Phlu Luang, was defeated by the Konbaung Dynasty in the Second (*) Burmese-Siamese War and was succeeded by the short-lived Thonburi Kingdom under Taksin the Great. For ten points, name this kingdom that ruled Siam from 1351 to 1767."
      ],
      "answer": "Ayutthaya Kingdom T"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A work by this author helped the popularity of the future king Charles I as it was the first public masque in which the Prince of Wales performed. This man contributed two poems to the opening of the (20 pts)",
        "First Folio, including “To the Memory of My Beloved.” Though this man had a complicated relationship with William Shakespeare, the King’s F Men performed this man’s work with Shakespeare himself appearing in (10 pts)",
        "Every Man in His Humour. For ten points, name this Elizabethan playwright who popularized the “comedy of humours” in works such as Volpone and The Alchemist."
      ],
      "answer": "Benjamin Jonson"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s dying question was “Where is God?” This man’s killer replied, “This is what you did to my friends,” referring to the four years of battle between the two that was A instigated by Emperor (20 pts)",
        "Zeno of the Byzantines. This man lost the Battles of Verona and the Isonzo to the man who killed him, Theodoric the Great. This man had earlier invaded Dalmatia and was implicated in the assassination of Julius Nepos. This man overthrew Orestes and led a successful siege of (10 pts)",
        "Ravenna to depose Romulus Augustulus. For ten points, name this first King of Italy."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Flavius Odoacer",
        "Odovacer"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man built the Ames Hydroelectric plant to power the Gold King Mine, and heRfounded the Duquesne Mining Company in Arizona’s Patagonia Mountains. At age 21, this man invented a “car replacer” and a reversible frog. The (20 pts)",
        "Union Switch and Signal Company was founded by this man who witnessed brakemen unable to stop two colliding trains, leading him to create a failsafe compressed air break. This man used (10 pts)",
        "AC transformers to compete against Thomas Edison’s DC power in the “War of the Currents.” For ten points, name this American pioneer in the electrical industry."
      ],
      "answer": "George Westinghouse, Jr. D"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A man with this surname was killed atop his horse “Fire-Eater” when a bullet struck an artery in his leg at The Peach Orchard. Another man with this surname was controversially replaced by John Bell Hood during the battle of (20 pts)",
        "Atlanta. That general with this surname was earlier wounded at the battle of Seven Pines, allowing Robert E. Lee to take command for the first time. The most famous general with this surname was slain attacking Grant’s troops on the first day of the Battle of (10 pts)",
        "Shiloh. For ten points, give the surname of Confederate commanders Joseph Eggleston and Albert Sidney."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Johnston",
        "Albert Sidney Johnston until “John Bell Hood” T"
      ]
    }
  ]
}